This interview is with Jack and Ryan
from the band AJR. They have more than
five billion streams on Spotify. More
than eight and a half million people are
listening to them on the platform every
month. And the music video for their
song World's Smallest Violin has more
than 170 million views. The story of the
band is the story of the internet. From
how they blew up on TikTok to how they
think about marketing and distribution,
YouTube, social media, and of course now
AI. We talked about all those things.
They told their story, shared their
thinking, and you'll notice that the
theme that runs through this
conversation is how do you actually
speak and communicate truth? Well,
that's what we talk about in this
episode.
>> All right, welcome guys.
>> Music is a funny thing because for some
music, you have live feedback of the
people in the audience when you're
playing live, but sometimes, no, you're
just making music. It's just the three
of you, the two of you and your brother.
>> And you don't have that feedback.
>> Yeah. I mean, we were just talking about
comedy. I've seen said a lot about
comedy that if you're writing a joke
thinking, "Oh, this will make people
laugh," the joke's going to die. And if
you write a joke and the joke makes you
personally laugh, the joke's going to
kill it on stage. I think we think like
that a lot. I know it sounds like, you
know, cocky to say, but like a lot of
the songs do make us cry as we're
writing it. Like a lot of the more
emotional ones, um, we're having the
exact reaction that we want fans to
ultimately have. We're dancing or we're
crying. Um, and that's kind of our
indicator of, okay, I think we're going
to be on the same wavelength as the
audience here.
>> Like, what's an example of of that? Ryan
is the sort of emotional lyric writer,
I'd say, between us. So, it comes from
him.
>> Yeah. I guess for the more emotional
stuff, I'm thinking I think a lot of
what we try to do now, especially in the
music, is right from uh character. We
talk about that all the time. Um we have
a we have a song on our EP that's uh
coming out called A Dog Song. That's
probably a good example of this that we
we knew we wanted to write. We both have
dogs that we love and they're like the
light of our life. And we knew we wanted
to write a song from our dog's
perspective. And exactly that reaction
is like this could be really funny and
silly and and so I laid down for a nap,
you know, like gimmicky and stupid, but
there's got to be an emotional way in to
write from our dog's perspective. And it
just hit us at a certain point. I'm
trying to remember what it was. It was
oh he the naivity in which our dog views
the things happening in our life the way
our dog thinks he's protecting us in
reality like if you zoom out we're
protecting him that's the character we
want to write from I got you guys I hear
like you're going through this tough
thing I brought you this stick did that
help like there's the emotion I think
that got us really excited about that
story
>> yeah and the naivity of watching a human
cry and not understanding why there's
something so emotional to that.
>> Something I did.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. It's almost like a little kid.
Like what's really emotional about that?
Like I have no idea what's happening,
but how can I help make it better? You
know, that's so funny. I love the laugh
that you have because that's always been
our process in writing.
>> When I first met my girlfriend, I showed
her some of our music and she like 10
seconds in there's like a funny line and
she's like laughing a lot and then it's
a portion about how I feel so lonely cuz
and I want to call my dad and then she's
like, "Oh." And we're like, wait, maybe
that's the style that we should start.
>> What's the song? Humpty Dumpty Humpty
Dumpty. You know the I was listen I
definitely got the melody wrong there,
but I was listening to that and and then
>> that's what the melody should have been.
>> You just,
>> okay, I'm going to join the band and
then yeah, you just start laughing and
that's what I love about you guys is you
have preserved the goofiness
>> among success. You know, generally
people become a little more buttoned up
and whatnot, but you guys are just goofy
people and that really shines through
the music and you don't often even think
of music and goofiness is coming
together.
>> Well, I think uh we love Pixar movies.
That's probably our favorite type of art
possibly. Um for exactly that reason.
It's like this is going to be a silly
movie about fish in Australia. Oh, it's
a movie about a dad learning to trust
his kid for the first time.
>> You're laughing. Then by the end it hits
you with a left turn and you're crying
all of a sudden. Um I think I think that
we are like so much of what becomes your
superpower started out as your weakness,
right? Like when you're a writer that's
like sort of finding your perspective is
I we can't be cool. Like you're saying
goofy, which is kind of the opposite of
cool.
>> Anytime we've tried to pretend we're
cool or wear sunglasses on stage in a
metaphorical sense, we just look like
we're wearing a costume. like it just
feels fake. You can audiences can smell
that from a mile away. And I think we
realized
if we can't be as cool as Drake and talk
about the cool things Drake talks about,
what's really our POV? What can we do
that maybe Drake can't? And I think it's
uh really empathizing, making you laugh
then cry, but just really letting you
know what the very uncool experience of
being a dog is or the very unsexy
experience of being in a relationship
could be like I think we found that
that's like sort of our voice, I guess.
>> And how conscious are you of this? And
how do you have that consciousness
help your work rather than being so
conscious of like who you are and what
you're trying to do that it's like ah
now we're not really producing stuff
from the soul anymore. It's sort of
coming from our minds.
>> Yeah. It's just a dangerous thing to go
down to go what would AJR do like what's
our what's this character? What would
they say in that? Right. That's almost
the death of
>> creativity.
>> Creativity right. Uh, I feel like
there's a few tricks that we've learned.
Um,
one being,
you know, to get away from that. What's
AJR's voice? Um, what's the most
embarrassing thing I could think of
about me? You know, let's go down that
route. I think that that's just the key
to writing in general or the kind of
>> most writing I would say. What's the
thing that embarrass that would
embarrass you most to say to a random
person on the street or to your best
friend? That has to be the next song
concept that we write about.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I think there tricks to get
away from digging yourself into that
hole of AJR's voice on top of AJR's
voice on top of a photo and then it gets
so diluted.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Let's follow that word
embarrassing because the thing about
embarrassing you're like ah I shouldn't
say that. You know AJR can't say that.
Hey, you know we're we're we're we're
famous. Like we can't say that. Like we
don't want people to know that. But then
at the same time you're like no that's
the thing that we're going for. So how
do you navigate that? Well, it just I
mean to start that I I think that
there's a moment in every writer's kind
of career where they do hit that point.
We we reached that that that wasn't what
we were writing about from when we
started. We were writing more like party
songs that we feel people could get on
top of a desk in a dorm to and that's
what good writing is and that and and it
did work for us in a little bit, you
know. Uh but then people stopped coming
to show or people didn't really show up
to shows or anything like that. People
didn't connect. They didn't really care
who was saying that and I don't really
care personally who's saying that. I
wouldn't have. Um, and then we realized
>> that
people feel the same things as you. And
it's this crazy realization that you
come to in writing that like if I write
about something embarrassing, odds are
that that person, the audience is going
to feel the exact same way or or really
understand what you're saying. And then
all of a sudden people started showing
up to shows as we started
>> and that becomes really addicting.
That's what we found like the little
embarrassing like maybe the first
embarrassing thing was weak like if you
even want to call it embarrassing we had
a song like I'm weak and what's wrong
with that like about sort of giving into
temptation right weak.
>> Yeah. Well, not I wouldn't even say
embarrassing. It's more just like here's
a vulnerable thing. That's an a personal
uncool thing to say. And then just like
little by little, we wrote a song called
Joe about uh a kid I went to high school
with whose name was actually Joe who I
still think about to this day even
though I don't even like see him
anymore, but it's like Joe, do you think
I'm cool now? I'm playing MSG. Do you
think I'm cool enough for you? Cuz I
idolized him so much in high school.
pretty embarrassing thing to admit if
you like listen to the song, but the
reward of finding an audience by going
this is the truthful me is like so
euphoric that it's like kind of the
reason to be alive. It's like I'm just
fully connecting to you now. And so that
actually if like I could give a tip to
writers like lean into that cuz it's
actually addicting. You're going to want
to go deeper and deeper and deeper until
you can you can't even write that stupid
the silly party song anymore cuz that
feels like it would be written by
somebody else. That's not something you
really are scared to admit. Um, we uh on
our last album uh I had a song called
Turning Out Part Three that um was about
just like a a whole like it went into
like sort of intimac intimacy issues
that I I had and like
>> um and my version of love was like
finding somebody where like that was
okay to like admit. I'm being really
vague here. I'm sure you know what I
mean.
>> And like just after putting that out and
seeing so much response of like I've
been through that too. having and nobody
writes songs about this [__] Like
like nothing makes you feel more
accepted and connected and like one big
organism with everybody else to just
like be yourself no matter how
embarrassing.
>> Yeah. I'm thinking a lot about the
moment in writing or speaking when you
kind of find you get to a place where
it's like
I'm not supposed to go there. I'm not
supposed to say that. You know, it's
like the breaks show up. You know, I'm
talking I'm talking. and you find that
place goes and what I'm hearing you say
is
you can actually push beyond that and
then that's really when you get to the
deep stuff because
>> what most what everybody feels versus
what they actually express there's a big
delta between those things
>> and
the wrong takeaway here is oh just like
wax poetic about all these sorts of
things like that can be really
overbearing.
>> What's wax poetic?
>> Trauma dumping is probably a better way
to put it, right? Trauma dumping is a
better way to put it. Thanks for the
clarification. And but there's a way of
you're talking about intimacy issues.
I'm going to focus on this really
specific thing.
>> Yeah,
>> really specific. And I'm just going to
go down and down and down and down
rather than the trauma dumping which
tends to be a little bit more broad in
scope.
>> Totally. Yeah.
>> And trauma dumping I feel like often
comes from a a self-centered place of
like my dad messed me up this much. Not
making fun of that, but like I think a
songwriter's job, a comedian's job, like
it's like I have this thing that's
really personal to me, but I just have
this instinct that a lot of other people
are quietly noticing or observing the
same thing or went through it and it's
going to strike a nerve with them. Um,
it's like the idea of like the word love
is not really interesting to us, you
know? It's like that is kind of what
you're saying of what is love? What is
this? That that doesn't really make us
feel much. It's the moment of talking
about intimacy. I think there was like a
quote, I forgot who said it, but like
when you're writing, it's not about like
you don't write about the brutality of
war. You write about a like a child's
burnt sock laying on the ground. I
forgot who said it, but that's like
that's on that one character, you know?
>> Yeah. Which is so much of what we try to
do with character cuz we we also like
we're not always just writing about like
the most specific thing that we went
through. Right now, like this most
recent EP is probably more of that.
We're more into that. But like
even when we're like um we have a song
called Inertia uh that is like turned
into like a fan favorite that's just
it's a list of examples basically of
like inertia just that we've observed.
It's like uh our friend that keeps
saying he's going to quit his bank job
and he's he never does or uh the couple
that we know that's keeps saying they're
going to break up but they're together
for the next 20 years.
the it's a huge concept inertia in
society, but it's what you're saying.
It's like zooming in on these tiny
little vignettes that you just know it
when you hear it. If it's phrased in the
right way with the right 10 words in a
row and the right melody, you're just
like, I believe you. I know exactly what
you're talking about and I have a friend
that went through that exact same thing.
Zooming in on that character.
>> Yeah. Tell me about musical theater and
pulling from there. You definitely see
it in the overture songs at the
beginning of your albums. How else have
you pulled from musical theater?
>> That was like our first love, I think,
before we even thought of forming a
band. We were like, we're so uncool, but
we we were like putting on Broadway
shows in our living room and making up
the lyrics and everything like that. So,
I think we couldn't not pull from it in
some way. Um, we feel like there's no
limitations uh in musical theater, and
there really aren't. Um, you you can
just
>> you can be as uncool as possible.
>> It it's it's Bohemian raps city. It's
>> change up times, talk about a random
thing, and then there's a new character
that comes in, and it's just constantly
changing, and we love that.
>> And it's also pure emotion,
>> undiluted by like society, where music
is at right now, or culture is at right
now. Like so many of our AJR demos you
would hear and you go that's like
literally a Broadway song and then
usually it's Jack's job. He comes in and
goes this is I can tell that my friends
are not going to think this is cool. Add
in a trap snare. Add in this thing
>> the villain in this.
>> Wait, so how does that happen? So you
come in like walk me through that.
>> Um
I I it's it's so hard to explain. It's
become so much gut feeling at this
point. It's what am I feeling? It's is
my brain am I is my attention going away
now? Is it too far in the other
direction? I I I don't know if it's so
much like uncool. It's just something
that I'm just not quite feeling is
music, you know? It's like if we go too
far in the musical theater of hold on
now we're even going to start having
dialogue in between like sides that it's
too far. And this is where the
partnership of us two really like is
everything and really works cuz like I I
think more often than not I'm starting
the songs like I'm making the like raw
clay. We have a song world's smallest
violin that like turned into probably
our biggest hit.
>> Yeah.
>> The first version I show Jack is a
perfect example of this like extremely
Broadway sounding. There were no sort of
808s in it production-wise but also like
the lyrics. Um there's a part in the
song that's like oh my god that's so
insane. Oh my god, that's such a shame.
The original lyric was like that's the
way it always is and that's the way it's
always been. The more I That was the
original lyric that I wrote which is
>> I don't know what did you hear in that
that you were like this lost my
attention.
>> It's like a stupid like teaching the
audience
>> I'm being sort of lectured at all of a
sudden. It feels very Broadway like I
need to see set pieces in order to
really understand this you know I need
to see other characters
>> and sometimes you just need to feel oh
my god that's so like just you need to
just say something sort of simple that
was that moment I think
>> but just yeah having that outside
perspective is like why there's so many
like Joel and Ethan Cohen why there's so
many partnerships that work well it's
like
>> somebody's
like Steve Martin says like your
subconscious writes and your conscious
edits Nice.
>> Right. I think so often I'm I'm the
subconscious and he's the conscious.
It's just I don't care what's cool. I
don't care about anything. Just this is
making me feel a lot then I bring you in
as an out right as an outside
perspective and you go you don't even
realize it's right in front of you,
Ryan. Put this here and this here and
change the and then we have a song that
people actually like.
>> Yeah. I think I'm more in touch with the
public uh than Ryan is honestly. Yeah. I
think that's what makes it a good
combination. Like I really observe what
people like in music and what people
don't like. I find it so fascinating. Um
>> how did you study that?
>> Oh, in college I just stared at people.
Truly, I'm not even kidding.
>> Why did you think to do that?
>> I thought it was so much fun. Um two
songs that sound almost exactly the
same. One people are standing on the
table, the other people are talking
through. And I was like, there's a DNA.
There's something living within music uh
that make people do that that's so
interesting to me. I kind of just like
fell in love with it. And it almost like
trained me to be in very in touch.
>> Were there certain cultural songs where
you got fascinated by why it resonates
so much?
>> Well, so often you call hits before they
become hits.
>> Yeah. And and god, that's that's
different though. That's like a truly a
gut feeling. Like Benny Blanco described
it perfectly when like he did an
interview recently and he was like it's
the feeling uh when you're about to kiss
someone and it's like that really good
nervousness where you're like leaning in
and he just absolutely nailed it. That's
exactly what I feel. It's the excitement
of something new. Take me to church
hose. I'm like, "Oh my god, wait a sec.
I I haven't heard something like this in
a while. This is
>> so new and I have a new energy in me."
And that's kind of what I feel when I'm
looking for hit songs or anything like
that or what is a hit. I know it didn't
fully answer the question, but I think
that's sort of a different kind of
world,
>> I guess. So, yeah. What was your
question?
>> If there was a song that you
got really interested in and saying, why
did this why did this hit so much?
>> I mean, it is songs like Take Me to
Church. Those are the most interesting
ones. when I forgot what the climate of
music was like, but let's say it was
like Soundcloud rap. That was the
climate of music. And then Take Me to
Church comes out or Hey hohei by the
Lumers. That was the only song of its
kind. Those are the ones that I've
really become fascinated by because the
whole tide of music is about to change.
What in the culture makes people want to
grab a guitar now and get up on a table
in a bar with their friends as opposed
to rage in the club? You know, that's
the stuff that I really like to study.
What you're saying that I hadn't really
thought about is how much the context
matters.
>> That basically there is a
time and place that the culture is in
right now.
>> Yeah.
>> And what you want to do is you want to
speak to that time and place. But if you
fully speak to it and give into it, then
you're
>> blending in with everybody else in
everybody else.
>> Whereas if you're too different, then
it's like
>> we're not this time and place right now.
I think that kind of falls back into
what you were saying about World's
Smallest Violin about the like don't go
too far, you got to put it back in the
setting, but also still world's smallest
violin doesn't sound like anything else.
It's sort of this silly
>> blue grassy dance song, you know, that
>> Yeah, I think that's the same kind of
world that we're talking about.
>> Yeah. And you're right, context like I
don't think it's a crazy miracle that
folk is has been so in in the last like
few years because we're all just like
doing this all day and there's
stimulation stimul like what do you want
if you're doing this all day and see
video after video? You want some kind of
calming music. You want to This sounds
so cynical, but you want to be able to
hear the guy talk over the music. So,
like of course it's going to be a little
bit more stripped down where it's like
maybe just guitar and a voice because if
it's a million instruments, you can't
hear your favorite influencer talk over
that. Um, you're also hearing it through
a phone speaker. A lot of unfortunately
a lot of music now. So, you want just
like three or four instruments as
opposed to 100 instruments to shine
through. Um, in retrospect, it's so easy
to kind of look back and be like, of
course folk was coming, but it's a new
kind of folk that speaks to Gen Z a
little more.
>> 100%. Because if you think of the rise
of EDM, I think of sort of the glory
days of that being 2011 to 2015. That
was peak iPhone. That was when the
iPhone was awesome. You would pull out
the iPhone, you pulled out magic. You
pulled out a portal to the cosmos and
the universe. And now you pull out your
iPhone and it's like it's like you're
being zapped with distraction. And now
it's sort of an enemy. So now what's
more in it's the nostalgia, it's the
folk, country music is booming cuz
that's what I want for music is I used
to want okay let's plug in to the matrix
of smartphone electronification and now
I want to tune out and retreat to the
golden age of nostalgia and simplicity.
No, it's just totally the climate and
people like either can predict it or get
lucky almost like
it almost like Noah Khan who who we know
and he's done such an amazing job at
kind of wrapping up what people are
feeling now. I feel like people are
could be a little moving away from the
phone. Throw away the phone, leave home
and go backpacking through, you know,
Oregon or something like that. And he's
really tapped into that. Um, it's it's
these moments, these predictors that are
really impressive in music. Yeah, I
think. Yeah.
>> And how often do you feel like people
are are judging? People are uh the
general population is going to be here
by the time I put this music out or how
often do you think people are just like
getting lucky and it's just how they're
feeling?
>> Even though if it's getting lucky, I
think that there's some people who are
just like it kind of goes back to what
we're saying like he feels that so the
rest of the public must feel it too.
this is something that he wants to
describe and odds are a lot of other
people are going to feel the same
similar to talking about embarrassing
things. A lot of people are going to
feel the same as well. I think society
is way more connected
>> uh than than people think.
>> Yeah. Well, I have friends who I would
say are bellweathers for the rest of
culture and then the question is how far
ahead are they of everybody else. So
>> the term bellweather
>> a bellweather is it's almost almost like
a canary in the coal mine. like the
bellweather sort of reflects what's
going on. The canary of the coal mine,
what they do is sort of a leading
indicator of what's going to happen. I
have a friend who's a designer and his
taste is always a few years ahead of the
culture. There's a guy who I follow
named Balry Sinvas and he's a
technologist. It's like sort of become a
joke that ah biology was right and it's
just how far ahead are these people and
I I don't know the music world that
well, but I guarantee there's got to be
musicians who are like that with sound
and lyric and whatever else. Yeah,
Kanye's the shining example.
>> Sure. Um Rick Rubin, absolutely. They
just have it. Some of them are just
>> If you look back at every Kanye, like
disclaimer, Kanye has gone crazy and
don't agree with anything he said. But
that would be stupid to erase how he's
the most transformative artist of the
last 20 years, right? Just because he
went crazy after that. Anyway, um if you
look at every album, he's like two or
three years ahead and then you watch
every other rapper sort of go, "Oh, I
guess hip-hop is leaning in more of like
a gospel direction now." Like two or
three years later. Um
>> and I think it's why everybody hears uh
at least for the last 20 years,
everybody heard um what's the one before
dark twist of fantasy? What's that?
>> Jesus.
>> Oh no, before.
>> Oh,
everybody hears that and goes, "What is
this garbage?" And then it takes
everybody like six months to catch up
and go, "Oh, now this is what hip-hop
is." And then suddenly Drake fully
sounds like 808s and heartbreaks. Um, it
takes a certain guts to just go, it's
like a version of just being
embarrassing and telling your truth.
It's just I this is where I think music
going slash this is my truth
production-wise and if it fails
horribly, I'm willing to die on that
hill. It's way easier to just sort of
follow the trend. Um, so I think that's
admirable.
>> When you're writing, do you feel, how
would you describe the process of
creating the wet clay? Is it when is it
frantic? When is it excitement? When
does it come from sort of a slow drip?
>> I I my friends like recognize it and and
call it work mode. Like Ryan's in work
mode. And I think they all notice that
I'm way less social. uh I'm sort of a
creature version of myself while I'm
like in that mode. Um because I turn and
I' I've heard this from other sort of
artists like and directors while they're
making a movie. It's like there's no
room in your brain to like make small
talk with anybody else. Like it doesn't
make you an [__] It just makes you
like sort of I don't know, you're a
robot and you switch into work mode. Um
to me, I'm constantly a sponge taking in
things. Um, I'm naked. Uh, I feel naked,
uh, in terms of how vulnerable I am. Um,
for the la while we were making this EP
for the last six months, like I found
myself so many times like going to Jack
or going to friends being like, "When
you said that, that was like really
offensive." Or, uh, uh, when I said
this, was was that joke taken wrong? I
feel really bad about that. That's what
I mean by like you're just kind of naked
because you're just wearing your heart
on your sleeve cuz you're constantly
trying to mine from yourself, from your
life, from your memories, from your
therapy sessions of what's going to make
good fodder for music. Um, and so I
guess when I sit down for the more
emotional stuff, I have to start from
somewhere, like with a dog song, I have
to start with, okay, there's a character
here that, right, thinks he's protecting
us. were actually protecting him. What's
this story? And I started writing a dog
song about our life. And um our dad got
sick and and passed away a few years
ago. And the song kind of came about of
our dog watching that happen and going,
um there's a verse that's like, uh, I
hope we don't move again. They lost half
my [__] Those dumb moving men. And
where did your dad go? Did they also
lose him? Well, I brought you this
stick. I hope that it helps. Um,
>> yeah, exactly. It's like, oh, a little
funny, a little duh. Yeah, exactly.
>> You just did the real time like exactly
what I wanted to reacting everybody.
>> Um, and uh I just found myself crying. I
just saw myself from the dog's
perspective and I just um I we have a
thing where if I know I have something
good, I text Jack uh the the eye emojis
that are like looking that way. Um
>> and I know let's go.
>> We we have something. It's time to
write. Yeah.
>> Um,
>> yeah. And I know if I'm crying, I know I
know it's we're if we get it right, it's
going to be truthful.
>> So, that work mode, it sounds like, is a
semic-conscious transition that you make
over the course of months.
>> Um, work mode isn't Tuesday from 8:00
a.m. to 12:00 p.m.
>> Oh, it's definitely not that. No, it's
not a slow transition. It's it's a fast
transition for us. like as soon as we
decided we're going to make an EP this
year and I knew we needed five songs and
I just needed to buckle down. It took a
day or so and it was then what you're
saying 4 months of me like if I think
back I can't even remember most of the
stuff that happened. All I was was just
in this kind of really volatile
emotional state.
>> Volatile. That's that's an interesting
word.
>> Yeah. I mean, I think you have to be. I
think like some songs are criers, but
you have to also be like hyper attuned
to yourself because if you're feeling
like this beat I just made is actually
like more badass. You have to be so
malleable that like, okay, now I'm not
crying anymore. I'm badass now. And
that's like such an unnatural thing to
for a human to do. But you have to
become a shell of yourself in order to
be that nimble. Um, we have a song on
this EP called The Big Goodbye that is a
perfect example of that where we we had
this track for a really long time that
uh samples this like auctioneer guy and
we wrote the song over and over again.
We wrote it as this kind of like party
bang kind of song. Didn't click. It
didn't feel right. We wrote it as like a
sillier more like did you ever notice
this kind of thing in society kind of
like inertia what I was saying song. Uh
it became more emotional at the last
second. We were like it's emotional plus
badass. Like that whole process is such
a mind [__] that you just have to be
able to pivot I suppose. Well there
becomes a moment where a song becomes
three-dimensional and it was two
dimensional the entire time.
>> Yeah. So and that's
>> what was that shift?
>> Um
I think it uh I don't know. I've never
thought about it before. It is a lot of
feeling
>> but we both felt it. We were both like,
"Oh, this now I believe this song as
they're trying to write a song for me."
>> Or it's something that I don't normally
think about and I try to put myself
outside and the song is kind of teaching
me something, you know? Maybe that's
when it becomes threedimensional.
>> Huh. Yeah. I don't think we've ever
really thought about this before of like
what is that moment? Yeah, it really is.
>> Cuz we have tried to write a bunch of
songs. They usually turn out like photo
copies of photocopies of AJR songs. Like
>> we wrote a song about how it's great to
be weak. Let's try writing a song about
how it's great to be insecure or
whatever,
>> right?
>> And that feels like we're just copying
ourselves and that feels very
two-dimensional.
But then the second we either find like
a real example or like
>> or twist or a twist,
>> right?
>> Then we're like, "This has to go on the
album." And then we know like we have
something great.
>> Yeah. Cuz we want songs to go like this,
just like you want a movie to go like
this. And if it's too long of a
monologue about how happy someone is,
you're probably going to zone out or
turn it off. When you were talking about
the two-dimensional to three-dimensional
shift, I was thinking about how in many
writing projects when you start you go
from you were doing the writing and
towards the end it's as if the piece
has a
a drive a momentum and then you start
listening to the thing that you're that
you've created and you are actually in
service of that.
>> Totally. It's it's it's the characters
kind of develop a life of their own,
right? And they start telling you
instead of you telling them what to do,
they start telling you what they want to
do next.
>> Um I think that it's definitely a part
in our music of we try to develop a good
character and I'm weak and a
>> dog song and then eventually it's like I
kind of know what would happen next,
what the next location is. Yeah. Yeah.
Create a bit of an arc for the
character. I think that might be it. I
think that's where the three dimension
comes in.
>> Huh. Yeah. Yeah. A lot of novelists say
that
towards the end the the character starts
surprising them.
>> Yeah.
>> And the story is taken off a life of its
own. Taken on a life of its own. And
they're responding to the way that it's
moving.
>> That must be the most fun feeling in the
world.
>> That must be so surreal.
>> Yeah.
>> I can't even imagine that.
>> Okay. So, I know you love making live
shows. How does that process come
together?
Yeah, live shows are something that we
think about the entire time we're
writing an album. Oh, wow. The entire
time. It's almost like the
>> album is the Broadway soundtrack to the
live show uh that that we're doing.
>> The tour is the end goal piece of art.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. That's what you're saying. And
the album is the soundtrack to that.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Um, every single time we
have a good song going, we we know and
we're like, as soon as we have a song
that's like not so good, we definitely
stop oursel and we're like, we know this
isn't going to go any further. There's
nothing else we could do. We throw it
away and it's a great feeling. Then we
start over. And then we have a song we
like, we immediately start talking back.
And on stage, you're going to be walking
on a treadmill and doing this with the
background.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Just for context for anybody
that doesn't know, we we try to lean
into our Broadway influence a lot, but
for these tours, we our our goal has
developed to just be like, let's put
stuff on stage that has never been done
before. So, we take influence from like
our love of magic. We have a lot of like
these sort of magic kind of illusions
that work their way into the songs. last
tour we had like a whole shadow puppet
thing where then the shadows came to
life and Jack was duetting himself on
stage and sort of a narrative throughout
that then ends with culminates with this
like big speech where you think back and
you go oh that thing that happened 45
minutes ago that came back that was an
Easter egg to this thing like that's
what we mean by like that's the end goal
piece of art um and so the songs we have
definitely like started reverse
engineering the songs knowing that the
finale for this album. We need a little
uh musical pause here so that we could
go, "Thank you, Charlotte." and take our
bow and then come back in with the
music. Like, we're definitely aware.
This is how we start the show. This is
how we end the show. This is a great
midpoint of the show. Uh for this one, I
feel like Jack is uh falling. So, we
should Jack have Jack like skydiving on
stage. We did something last where like
he's like has these two 3D video walls
and he's in the middle hanging from a
wire and there's this illusion where
he's like skydiving. clouds on both
sides like rushing past me so it looks
like I'm falling and
>> um and it's just become our favorite
thing to do ever to make the these
tours.
>> And do you work with a choreographer?
>> No, we really just do it ourselves.
Yeah.
>> It's such a fun process of the what if.
It's like two guys in their underwear at
home just be like what if he's this and
what if I'm doing this? It's like a
weird drug trip that
>> Yeah. Yeah. And it also feels a lot like
when we were young that we like we
didn't have any video games or anything
growing up. So, I think we were just
bored all the time. Yeah. And so, we
were constantly just like making up
games or putting on plays for our
parents or we went through a puppet
phase where we loved puppets and we went
through a lightsaber phase and a magic
phase and like
>> we're still in the lightsaber phase.
>> But we're just like tapping into all of
our cool loves when we were kids, but
just making them on a grand scale now.
So, what have you learned about making
music from that live feedback?
>> Um, I think that it's to not be afraid
to switch up time signature and to not
be afraid to go in another direction.
Uh, I think it's difficult these days to
keep people entertained. Um, and I think
that doing a show where you don't know
what's going to come next is really a
good road to go down. And then that also
translates to that also goes over to the
music as well.
>> Switch-ups like this have make you kind
of lean in and go, "Wait, I didn't know
that was going to happen. Where's it
going to go next?"
>> So, I think that there's a good parallel
there.
>> Yeah. I think we're finding like more
recently we're sort of bored by verse,
chorus, verse, chorus, bridge, chorus,
which is like the typical structure of a
song.
>> Every like no judgment to anybody that
does that, but like I don't think any of
the songs on this new EP adhere to that
uh structure. And I think some of that
has to do with what you're saying live.
Like we're like, you've already heard
this chorus two times. You don't need to
hear this chorus again. Let's do a crazy
outro with this weird thing where we're
playing on the sampler and like I'm
seeing a human being and you're reacting
better to that than a third chorus.
>> The iPhone ringtone remix.
>> Oh, throwback.
>> So good.
>> That is a big throwback. I love that.
>> That was so good.
>> Thank you. And I think that that was
where you guys really nail it, which is
I'm laughing and I'm vibing to it at the
same time.
>> Totally. And and it's like, is someone's
phone ringing on stage, too? There's the
Start with the confusion, too, you know?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I think um we're really we're big
fans of Magic, but we're big fans of uh
like Pen and Teller
>> cuz they show you how they're doing the
trick while they're doing the trick.
like they're showing they're
deconstructing the art for you while
giving you the dopamine you need to say
that was great art. And I think so often
that's what we want to do. like we have
these making ofs that has now become
like a staple that we do every tour
where like we're breaking down how we
made this song and there's like all
these visual elements and we're like and
uh then we're in the library and now
there's like a set piece over here and
we're in the library and uh a book falls
and we're like let's sample that book
and we tell the story basically of how
we made a song while we're building out
the song. Um and I just we see people's
reactions. It's really fun as an
audience to be confused, to suspend your
disbelief a little, to be like, "Oh, I'm
starting to recognize that song. I hope
it is the song that I think it's going
to be." And then to maybe throw them off
or maybe explode into that
>> or to predict it and be wrong cuz
audiences secretly love that, right? No
one wants to be right. They they want to
they think they want to be right and
then they want to be, "No way. It wasn't
the thing that I predicted, right?" You
know,
>> we're like transparently showing you the
skeleton of the human while being like,
"Isn't this the coolest human ever?"
Well, one of the things that is very
clear is that
by looking at the way you guys have done
things, it just reveals so much about
the world that we live in, how the
culture has changed. And it used to be
that the relationships between fans and
the their favorite musicians, there was
such a distance between them. M and now
we're talking and even coming into this
it's you guys allow yourselves to be
known through interviews, through the
live shows, through a bit more of an
improvisational style, much less much
less polished and everything you're
saying speaks to how much the modern
world has changed. You're even talking
about making of videos.
>> Yeah.
>> I don't think those were nearly as big
of a deal 20 years ago compared to now.
>> I think you're right.
>> Yeah. No, we were obsessed with the Lord
of the Rings behind the scenes. I don't
know if you've ever seen those, but like
>> we watched that more than actual
>> more than the movie of how they made the
miniatures and how they did the force
perspective and we were like, "Why is
this not more popular? This is
>> because then we watched the movie and we
like the movie 10 times more cuz we
like, oh, that's miniature."
>> Froto is like 10 feet behind him
actually, you know? Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Um, but there's a middle line.
Like I think that exactly our experience
with Lord of the Rings. We like Lord of
the Rings more after knowing that that
castle was only this tall.
But if I got that castle and I could
play with it now and then I'm like this
is the same thing in the movie that now
that's ruined the experience. I don't
know how well this metaphor is working
out. But no, I get what you're saying.
>> Right. There's like a certain level
where we still an artist should be
>> up here
>> and and and the audience should be down
here because they want it that way. They
want we're not crowdfunding. What should
our songs be about everybody? Like then
why do you come to us as as artists? I
think you're coming to us because we've
worked for a really long time to like
try to have a unique POV. Like I don't
think it should all be crowdsourced. I
don't think it should all be fully
transparent, but that's why I think the
making of the making of is art unto
itself. Like at the risk of sounding
pretentious, right? It's like I'm not
just like showing you my ProTools
session. I'm telling you a story that's
fun, that's making maybe enhancing your
like of the song, right?
>> So, I think that's what we try to keep
doing. Let's have you listen to the song
and notice these little details that we
worked hard on, but not just give you
the whole ProTools session.
>> Was there a moment when you were on
stage and you heard people singing and
you were just like, whoa, this is we've
this is really a thing now.
>> Yeah. Um it was 2005 was the moment we
decided to be a band and we were like
street performing and right like that
kind of thing. Um playing shows around
New York that no one was at. Um
>> and then in 2017 we had our first we
started putting out that music that we
were talking about before the more
vulnerable embarrassing kind of stuff.
People started liking it. Then we got on
stage in Orlando um Florida for the
first date of our like tour then after
we put that out. And I think we were
expecting an opening crowd like because
we were so used to it, you know, people
just like let's show up and see what
what's good.
>> We're going to have to win them over.
>> And we came out and there was only like
200 people there and just every single
lyric and I remember just like being
thrown back to the back wall and I was
like there is no way this is happening
right now. This is in in 10 years this
hasn't happened.
>> Um that was the show at a place called
The Social I think in Orlando. That's
right.
>> And it blew our mind. Really? Wow. I
can't even imagine that. That is one of
the most unique things about music. You
make it in silence. You work on it. You
work on it. And then you get to go out
and people
sing back
what you've written. Did you feel that
same show?
>> Yeah. That was a moment where it was
like, let's just do this forever. Like
>> definitely. Let's just hope that all the
we put on a good enough show that all
these people tell one friend the next
time we could play double and double and
double and double. Um that's been really
like our the long game like with AJR. I
think it's really like uh Chris Martin
from Coldplay said like the reason
they've stuck around so long is that
they've never been the coolest thing.
They've always been something to be
discovered.
>> And I love that. I don't think that we
were meant to be uh Justin Bieber. Like
I just don't like I don't think we're
interested in it. Like I think that we
want to just I think that can be really
crippling to be that big.
>> That's what I think we can be.
>> And that's just not who we are. We just
can't. Uh I think if we want to keep
writing songs from dogs perspectives, we
can't like get to that level of Ed
Sheeran. Um and I think we're really
proud of that. I think we're really
proud of how slow it's been and year
after year just like slowly growing and
having these core fans cuz it's a scary
industry now especially we could talk
about like Tik Tok and all of that but
like in the last like four years the
industry has just like is just totally
different. Nobody knows what they're
doing.
>> Talk about that.
>> No
off uh we watched it in 2020 just like
before 2020 was this is our single.
we're gonna push our single to radio and
see how it does. It just felt so much
simpler. And now you don't really choose
your own single, at least like in our
camp. Now it's like you make music that
you want to make and hope that something
goes viral. And it's there's one weird
avenue to having a hit song and it's
social media. It's not.
>> Man, that's so strange.
>> It's so strange. kind of cool because
it's happened to us a bunch of times and
that's like it's a great feeling and
then when it doesn't happen to you you
feel like the piece of [__] and you're
and the embarrassed and a little
embarrassed because it's all about
self-promotion. It's like I pushed this
one so hard and it didn't work. The
image that came to mind for me was some
sort of game of roulette where you're
just playing game of roulette. You got
to hope that something works. And then
the value of having an audience is it's
like the NBA draft. you get more kind of
balls that you can have for the game of
roulette, but still if nothing pops.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. And it's especially weird coming
from us cuz we started in the in the
days where radio was like the thing and
you had to travel to every single radio
station twice in America and shake the
hands and meet their kids and do a
million interviews and that's what we
really got used to. Um, and then it was
the streaming services too. Go into
Spotify and talk to them about it and
have a hit on Spotify. And that felt a
little more understandable to us. Yeah.
>> Um, and then transitioning into this
world where it's like radio is kind of
less prevalent than it used to be. Uh
it's been very confusing for us
>> and we're also now competing with
uh a Bill Maher and Trump and this and
like suddenly our competition is totally
not other musicians anymore. It's such a
weird thing. You have to try to catch
people's attention with a song uh while
they're watching a visual of something.
Well, it's crazy that that you would say
that because the idea of a song being
the point of it is to catch somebody's
attention. I mean, besides a jingle from
like a 1960s radio ad, that wasn't what
artists were thinking.
>> It's not what music is. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. It's a cra
it is just the industry now. I think
it's like
>> I think we're there everywhere in
society a little bit where it's like the
new Lilo and Stitch movie is sort of a
commercial for the old Lilo and Stitch
movie, right? You go going I remember
seeing that when I was a kid. It's like
the Tik Tok is a commercial for the song
which is a commercial for the tour. Um,
>> right. It's very weird and it's in some
ways it's not artistic and we try to not
let it affect us. I think we naturally
before Tik Tok were writing tick- tocky
type of songs for exactly the reason
Jack is saying with the switchups and
with like cuz we like showing
deconstructing and showing one
instrument at a time and making weird
beats and stuff and writing relatable
things like if those are the if that's
the agenda to make a tick tocky song we
were already doing it anyway. So, I
don't feel like we're like selling out
trying to write Tik Tok music at all.
Um, but you have to just be so you have
to fight against that instinct of all
that matters is catching people's
attention.
>> Totally.
>> And that's why it really helps that we
have this fan base. I think if we
didn't, we'd be like falling and
wondering who we can catch whose
attention. But like for us a little bit,
the Tik Tok stuff feels like the cherry
on top of the fans and the tours and the
community we've already built.
>> I want to go back to what you were
saying about that's not what music is at
all. Talk to me about that.
>> Uh music is natural. Music is just you
sit down and you're feeling something,
so you want to write it. It's not to c
it's not a jingle. It's not 10 seconds
that'll capture people's attention.
That's not the thought process that goes
into writing in good music. It's uh it's
what we said. It's writing about
something embarrassing. It's writing
something thinking that maybe no one
will hear it. And that's okay. And
that's something that we get into a lot.
And that's like often when we're the
most happy, too, of like we write a
really weird song and we're like, if no
one likes this, we're going to be okay.
We like it. We're
>> we really like it and we're proud of it.
We had a song called The Trick. Um which
was probably the least listened to song
we've ever put out or something like
that. Like fans did not seem to like it.
We got a lot of like complaints about it
of like cuz there's like a weird
high-pitched voice and like I don't know
about this one guys, but we just love
that song so much and I don't feel bad
at all.
>> Um that the fans don't love it cuz we
really really liked it and we were
really proud of it. I think that that's
what music is. Um and Tik Tok can really
make you feel embarrassed and ashamed.
Um and it's not something that we want
to feel, you know.
>> Talk to me about the concept of truth
because it's very core to what we've
been talking about this conversation is
speaking truthfully. But when we think
of truth, we think of Plato and Socrates
and Aristotle and making sure that the
logic adds up and stuff like that.
You're making a good rigorous argument.
But there's deeper levels of truth that
we've been talking about in this
conversation. We've been talking about
truth of the truth of what you feel. And
then as you were talking there, it was
like you're sitting down and you're just
making sounds and the sounds are somehow
true to what you're feeling, what you're
processing, what's going on.
>> Um I think well one I think we it's
constantly changing for us. Uh, I'm
we're writing totally different songs
now that like I'm in my 30s, Jack's
about to be 30. Like
it just our truth is just totally
different from when we wrote weak and we
were in our early 20s. Um, I think it's
it's pretty subjective. Um, I think that
so one of the reasons that I'm we get
asked about like AI and music sometimes
>> and I'm not really worried about AI and
music. Um because of exactly what we're
talking about because I think that when
you believe
when something about the way an artist's
vocal cords are shaped that when Randy
Newman goes uh I will go sailing no more
from Toy Story. Like I just believe the
combination of his voice and the chords
and the and the the take he got and the
melody and the lyrics and I can't
describe why. Right. I just believe him.
And if uh Josh Groin sang that and when
I will go sailing no more whatever. I
love Josh Groin but I wouldn't believe
that as much. I would believe he's
performing that line because it doesn't
quite fit with him and he didn't quite
like believe it in that moment. I feel
that AI is is only ever going to take
Dual Lia plus Billy Eyish plus Miley
Cyrus and like find some nebulous middle
of all the artists that doesn't have a
POV is just like sort of like a basic
conglomerate of all of the artists. And
I don't get me wrong, I think as AI gets
better in music, I think music is going
to sound more and more different. I
think that's definitely going to happen.
the way like art now looks different.
I'm scrolling and I see art that I know
is like has that AI too perfect thing to
it and maybe the first time I saw it I
was like cool AI Chad GBT can make that
and now I'm so bored by it cuz there's
no feeling behind it and like while we
were while we were looking for an album
cover for this EP we we often like find
artists on Instagram and I think we
found ourselves going that one looks too
AI that one looks too AI and we ended up
going with an artist that created did
this this picture of a of a reunion that
is how a a family reunion feels as
opposed to how just here's how a family
reunion looks the way a computer could
make it. Um,
>> and you couldn't type that into chat GPT
of how does a reunion feel? What are the
mixed emotions that come with a family
reunion?
>> Happy and sad.
>> No, that's not I want to feel something
deeper than that.
>> I want to feel and I can't describe why.
And I think just as long as we can't
describe why someone like you by Adele
makes us cry and then this one doesn't,
like I I don't know. I think music
probably is going to get better and
better because it's going to get more
auristic, if that's a word. Like it's
going to become more and more from one
person's point of view as opposed to
here's a general pop song that everybody
can relate to that maybe Chad GBT could
have written.
>> Mhm.
>> The way art is going in that. Do you
have musician friends who are excited
about using AI and they're using it in
their art and they're like, "Hey, check
this out. Check this out." We used So,
there's a program uh called Kits AI
where you can basically like sing and
then you make it sound like this girl
and you can input a lot of data of we
did it with Jack's voice and we saw fans
doing it. Like here's Jack singing Hey
There Delila. And like it's a cool party
trick, but it actually helped in the
writing process cuz I was writing a
song. It might have been dog song. I I
think I was writing a dog song. And
often when I'm writing it, I'll record
me singing a demo with my voice and I
wanted Jack to sound to hear what it
sounds like with him singing it without
him actually having to sing it. So that
what he could go in and actually
re-record it. But like in that process
of making a cool song, I basically like
Jack was able to record it without
actually recording it, no creativity was
taken away from us, but it was like just
like a cool little tool to use, that's a
good use of it, I think. But like a fan
putting out a Drake song and I I feel
like that's kind of a mess.
>> Yeah. As soon as you're like replacing
people, like
>> that was our end goal with AI to replace
musicians.
have it do like the shitty work that no
one wants to have to do. Um,
>> but I just I really feel that
historically it's never like the answer
is never now anybody could make a
professional sounding song. It's now the
definition of a professional sounding
song shifts. That's just with every new
technology. When uh when Photoshop first
came out and you could put like a paint
filter, I don't know, 2003, I showed my
dad that and it was like, look, I I
acted like I painted this picture of me.
It was cool for about a day and then you
move on and that effect is no longer
cool. And I kind of think at an
accelerated rate that's going to be
happening where art is probably going to
get more and more personal and move
faster, but probably get better and
better and more human as it runs away
from the computer. Yeah. What's going to
be cool is I made this
>> and I made this. You can tell because
it's exactly me as a person. There are
off notes and it changes and it's not
like anything you've heard before.
>> Well, the offotes thing is really
interesting to think about how
you don't want to have offnotes for the
sake of having off notes.
>> But off notes are also a kind of proof
of authenticity. It's the same thing in
writing. When I read something with
typos or there's some weird
idiosyncrasies, I'm like, "All right,
you actually wrote that. You know what I
mean? But also,
>> I can't imagine anything more annoying
than somebody putting typos and
idiosyncrasies after having written with
AI to be like, "Got you, dude." Like,
that would be such a dystopia.
>> It really would.
>> Yeah. Um I want to believe that you
could see through that. I don't know.
Maybe I'm being optimistic. the maybe
the typos thing is tough cuz you know
it's just in writing in a book but like
I think you'd be able to tell if a voice
crack or anything like that was
>> on purpose verse they were just feeling
the emotion
>> I don't know you could just tell like in
conversation I could tell that I believe
you and you you really believe what
you're saying
>> I want to believe that that's the same
with art
>> yeah
and a major thing is when we're at your
shows we want to be connected with you
guys I
This is probably Thank God I don't work
in the music industry. I better be
cancelceled for what I'm about to say.
But I do think that music serves a few
different functions. And sometimes the
function is actually it's just purely
functional, which is I'm working and
there's some people sitting next to me
at the co-working space and I just need
some sound so that I can't hear their
dang conversation that doesn't distract
me. And I go on YouTube and I'm like,
"Focus piano." And actually, I don't
really care if it's AI generated. I just
need to not hear them. Do you know what
I mean?
>> And then at the same time, there's
artists who I really adore where part of
why I love their music is because I feel
a connection with them as people. And
for them to be making things with AI,
I'm like, "No, I've come to this for
you, Jack and Ryan, and now you're going
to outsource this to AI." That's that's
that's a complete betrayal of the
implicit contract that we have going on
here.
>> I totally agree. And for what purpose?
So they could save a few days of time
like why is the goal of making a song I
can make it this fast? Like this only
took me 5 seconds to make with AI verse
the two weeks. Like that's the goal.
That's where we're headed in the music
industry. I I don't think so. I totally
agree with what you're saying about the
betrayal. Like good music is like it's a
conversation.
It's
it's passing on like wisdom.
It's a cry for help. Like a computer
doesn't know what any of those things
are. It could replicate it by taking
Randy Newman's cry for help and Randy
Carile's cry for help and combining it.
But that's not my cry for help.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. It'll never perfect that. Maybe
it'll get lucky once in a while, but
it'll never perfect it
>> just like it'll never per uh predict
trends too. Going back to Hoser, I I
have with complete confidence that uh
chat GBT could not have written that
song to be maybe by accident if you
typed in a certain kind of thing, but it
could never predict predict the next
culture and what's coming next. That is
just purely human what human is feeling.
They're only going to go by what was
popular. Maybe it's a Beatles sounding
thing and that's not how songs the new
wave of songs happen
>> of real like long lasting songs. Yeah.
>> How do you guys think about
improving your craft and retrospectives
when things you could have done better
>> and how do you think about those
retrospectives?
>> I see.
Um,
>> and this general process of improving,
you know, you you're better artist now
than you were 15 years ago. And part of
that is subconscious, but I'm curious
about the conscious part of what
accounts for that improvement.
>> Wow, it's a good question. Um, I think
it an uninteresting answer is that it
just kind of comes naturally with
growing as people, especially in the
style of music that we make. We're going
to keep being honest no matter what. And
I think number one, it's going to become
natural because we're going to have new
experiences that fans relate to. Number
two, we become really obsessed with
beating what? Not beating, but like
doing something totally different than
what we did last time.
>> Yeah. That's, you know, that becomes
like the death of creativity when we're
like, "Okay, we did an overture for the
last album. How are we going to beat the
last overture with with an overture on
this album?" Right. And that's so
crippling to us that it makes us like
not even want to write. It's so like
hard to think how are we going to beat
like it's a competition between the
thing we put out last year and this
year. So often we find oursel just
taking a left turn and going this album
actually is not going to have an
overture. It's going to have a whole
different thing that you can't compare
it to.
>> And it's worked out for us. Honestly, I
think that that could go wrong. Um but
we've learned that that has always
seemed to work out for us.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And it's just like we keep
saying truth, but it's like have
like write something that you can defend
in front of a jury, right? Like we have
some songs that I I don't want to say
regret, but like I can't defend. Um, we
have a song called Thirsty that like uh
is like silly and it sounded like 2013
and it's like the hook is like thirsty
thirsty Thursday and yodelling and stuff
and we were experimenting and there's
been like countless Tik Tok trends about
how it's the worst song ever made and
not that that it doesn't hurt me but I
can't get on the stand and defend that's
actually how I was feeling Thursday.
But a lot of these other songs, if there
was to be a trend about um a dog song,
how it's the worst song ever made, I
could stand on the on in front of a jury
and go, "It's actually how I was
feeling,
>> so [__] all of you." Like, "This is my
truth." And I think that's probably just
something that we've learned. It's just
like keep saying your truth and then you
can't possibly have regrets. And any
kind of hate, which every artist gets
hate now. It's just like the culture of
that. any kind of hate just bounces off
of you because you're like, "What do you
mean? I was just being myself. I can
fully defend that till the end of time."
>> You guys seem remarkably secure in these
things. And that must have been a
process of
I would presume there were times when
you had gotten hate and you're like,
"Man, we should maybe we shouldn't go
that route. Maybe we shouldn't be like
that." And now it seems like you've
overcome
something where you're just like, "We're
just going to be these people." Or maybe
you just always had these spines of
steel that I just cannot relate with.
>> Definitely not. It definitely hurt us at
first and then I think we quickly
realize that the things they hate about
us are the things that we love
>> that we love about ourselves. Exactly.
Yeah.
>> At the end of the day it feels like okay
I guess we just wouldn't be friends with
this guy. Um and uh I think you could
zoom out and uh realize it's not hating
us as people. It's just hating the
music. And in the moment it seems
watching a video it seems like they [__]
these guys, they're pieces of [__] and
whatever.
>> Um,
>> but it's not really that. There's kinds
of music I would never get on the
internet and [__] on songs I think
that's absolutely ridiculous and a waste
of time, but there's songs that I really
don't like and I hate and don't ever
want to listen to again and that has
nothing to do with the person that that
made it.
>> Yeah. And we've also just seen so many
of our favorite artists put out their
first album and it's so unique and then
they naturally get a lot of hate because
it's unique and then their second album
is like apologizing for how unique that
first album was and like okay now I'm
going to sound like the rest of hip-hop
or okay I'm just going to do an emo one
cuz that will give me less hate. And
it's like for us, we're like, "No, you
you had something that was real." And
you, then inevitably th those artists
often like go down in popularity after
that because they're it's a race to the
bottom of trying to sound like everybody
else. For some reason, we were very
aware of that this whole time of being
like, "No, no, we're just going to keep
being unapologetically oursel, right?"
>> Yeah. So, you have a new album coming
out now, and how are you thinking about
distribution and marketing? How has that
changed over time?
Um, yeah, social media is just like a a
thing that we've had to wrap our heads
around. I know we talked like about Tik
Tok. Like, it's also a really cool
thing. Like, World's Smallest Violin
wasn't supposed to be a single ever. It
was the weird deep cut for the fans and
now it's like our top song that we've
ever made. Three years ago, we made
that. It took what, two years for it to
start being noticed. The good part, um,
another one that got big on TikTok was 5
years before it started getting big.
Yeah, I think about 2018 and then 2023
it started.
>> You guys must be super unique
>> in how long it takes for some of your
songs to get popular. Is that normal?
No.
>> Yeah, it's pretty normal these days. I
think Lizo uh what's the song?
>> Truth Hurts.
>> Truth. Truth Hurts. Yeah. Yeah. I think
she made that in 2016 and it got big in
like 2021 or something like that. I mean
look at like Fleetwood Mac. They're like
the biggest band ever now because all
their music. ABBA. Aba. Abba. I don't
know how to pronounce it, but but
they're like the biggest band ever now
because of Tik Tok. I mean, they were
always huge, but now they're like the
biggest modern pop band. It It's pretty
common. And definitely it's easy to cry
like to lament the old industry where
you picked her single, but also like
that's kind of a cool new industry where
you get to just make a lot of songs that
you like and go live your life and hope
that in a couple years one of them like
blows up and crunches down history to
like forget that five years passed and
just goes, "Oh, AJ's blowing up again."
Like there's some optimism to it,
>> right?
>> Because you can never fail because
there's always just the chance that
tomorrow it could blow up.
>> Yeah. You know, that is nice that you
can put stuff out and many years from
now could be taken up because that is
almost the antithesis of social media.
Social media is this kind of constant
grind. Things don't get rediscovered.
>> Um that that that's one of the great
because there there's there's negatives
positives. Honestly, we've talked about
a lot of the frustration, but there's a
lot of real positives with this. When
back in the times of when radio was like
the thing, if your song was like they
called it done at radio, like down a lot
of spins and they're not going to play
it anymore. Your song was never heard of
again. Never. You don't even know who
that person is or or not person what
that song is. Um,
>> and it's this the total opposite these
days. Anything can happen. Someone can
use it in a trend. world's smallest
violin was used started in like a trend
of anime artists showing their work like
I'll blow up into smitherines and it
started like cutting on the beat of
different pieces of art that's just so
unbelievably random and then all of a
sudden it blew up from there. There's no
other time in in history where that
could be.
>> Well, this what's so weird about the
internet is
you could basically categorize the
internet as ephemeral and permanent. And
ephemeral and permanent are antonyms
>> and yet the internet's both.
>> It's like just a living thing
that we're all a part of that.
>> Yeah. I don't know what I'm picturing.
I'm picturing like a swirling like Come
on, imagine this with me. What are we
looking at here?
>> Like that.
>> Yeah. It's just like constantly rolling
and like I think being an artist now I
kind of think being in any industry now
is like with AI is like okay I'm rolling
with the punches and I'm ready to pivot
with what people decide it is in right
now. Um and I'm still being myself all
along. It's hard and more fun at the
same time.
>> And what are the economics of AJR in
terms of where revenue profit comes
from? because you were saying earlier
that a song is an advertisement for the
tour
>> and then merch factors into it. So, how
does that all work out?
>> Yeah, that that sounds really cynical. I
forgot I said that. But, um uh yeah, you
don't make a lot of money with streaming
unless you're like Ed Sheeran. Unless
you're just like in the billions of
streams.
>> Um
>> and does that bother you or is that just
that's how it is?
>> God, we don't know the ins and out. I
mean, I don't know the ins and outs.
>> Yeah. Uh we we'll tell you our surface
level understanding but like
>> uh for our first many tours we lost
money so it was like especially cuz we
were like bringing cool effects thinking
>> okay we'll we'll lose money this tour
but I hope they tell friends about in
the next tour we could play a little
bigger. We very much played the long
game with the tour that has worked out
for us like uh you know financially or
whatever that like now we're able to
like play arenas and amphitheaters and
stuff and actually like make that money
back. So, that was cool that like we
were right about this very long, you
know, 15-year risk we were taking. Um,
>> yeah, the songs I think if you add up
all the streaming and the music videos
and stuff, you probably make like some
money, but it's definitely not what it
used to be. Um, you make money when your
song gets in a commercial, that money is
still very like fertile.
>> Yeah, you guys have been in a lot of
commercials.
>> Yeah, that's the kind of thing like that
world is so like when you're in, you're
in. And like we were in a Microsoft
commercial and like they must have like
internal conversations among all those
music supervisors where they're like
something about AJ's music sells tech.
Yeah.
>> Right. So then like Apple asked us to
use Bang in their commercial. Um so
we've been really fortunate with that.
Um
>> I'm trying to think. Yeah. Merch makes
money.
>> Merch does. It's it's it's so much
touring these days. It's touring. Yeah.
>> That's why it's it's a big reason why
you're seeing so many people going on
tour. It's just the way to make money.
>> Yeah.
>> That's so funny. AJR, you know, you make
music and then all of a sudden it's like
the Samsung Galaxy S17 and both there's
something cool about that and then also
there's
>> I mean it's honestly how I feel with ads
for the show sometimes. I'm like, "Oh,
that's kind of cynical." You know, my
life's work will then be to sell, you
know, some sort of it's how you fund it.
I don't know. It's just sort of the
world we live in.
>> Yeah. Um Yeah. Yeah, I feel like that
probably like when smaller artists ask
us for advice, it's like
write a million songs,
write a lot and tour a lot and play a
lot of shows for people that don't come
for just a few.
>> When you say write a lot, what does that
mean? Does that mean you sit down from
9:00 a.m. to 12:00 p.m. every single
day? It means you walk around with a
notebook. What does it actually mean to
write a lot? Right. It's write a lot of
bad songs is is the idea, you know. Uh
and it's such an uncomfortable feeling
to sit in that and you makes you feel
like a failure and inadequate, but
that's just truly the only way. I'm sure
every writer has said this. It's truly
the only way to get better or the
thousand bad songs.
>> Yeah. And a thousand songs where you
could clearly see, oh, you guys are just
copying the Beach Boys with this song.
Like,
>> don't be afraid to wear your influences
on your on your sleeve. Naturally, the
first thousand, you know, 500 songs you
write are just going to be like copies
of your favorite artists. And that's
okay. But now you have those skills in
terms of writing, in terms of producing
you. I feel like I know how to implement
a hint of Frankie Valley like whatever
because I made a fully Frankie Valley
song 15 years ago. So now I could just
like take that little tool and implement
it into what's the song that like week
where
That is that Frankie Valley kind of tool
that I had. I knew that our voices sound
good with distortion and that kind of
high falsetto thing. So like it's doing
it a lot and then you get really bored
of copying your influences and you watch
your friends reaction and it doesn't
feel so good when they go, "Oh, were you
listening to a lot of Arcade Fire when
you wrote this?" Like you feel a little
like uh ashamed, right? You feel like,
"I'm not an artist. I'm just like a
proxy for Arcade Fire here." So, you
then start
really working on what can I bring to
the table that no one else can.
>> Mhm. What are the pros and cons of you
guys not being classically trained?
Taking music lessons when you're a kid
being I don't really like this and we're
going to teach ourselves.
>> Yeah. I mean, there's that imperfection
that we were talking about. There's
that. I feel like when you're
classically trained, you kind of get
conditioned that you miss a note, start
over,
>> you know, like, yep, you're you're you
got to be 100% on and you got to punish
yourself and it's got to be perfect
every single time.
>> Yeah, totally.
>> Um, there's also like
>> what's like it's called like the Dunning
Krueger effect where like you're so
naive that you
>> think you know a lot. you think you know
a lot and often those are the successful
people because they don't know how
difficult the road is actually going to
be or like they don't know what they
don't know so they just like go for it.
That to me is like the history of us.
It's just like uh if we had more
knowledge growing up of this is the
correct chord to go here. Uh we wouldn't
have taken all the musical risks that
we've taken and switch up time
signatures or um I don't know. We bend
genre a lot I think and we're very like
I don't care like just something in my
brain and our brains are like I don't
feel that anything is so sacred. I feel
like why not take yodelling and combine
it with classical piano and beatboxing
and see how that sounds. And I think a
lot of people's brains probably if
they're a little more educated don't
naturally work that way cuz they're like
yodeling came from Scandinavia in 1600
and that has nothing to do with
beatboxing which came from Brooklyn and
like
>> to me it's just like does it sound cool
>> and that's the benefit of living in a
post-modern 2025 world where you can
just everybody's doing it on TikTok like
this random person can combine
beatboxing and this and this and see if
it sounds good and then it might be
viral trend. So, why can't the artists
do it, too? Um, honestly, I think that a
con is that we tend to rely on the kind
of the same chords and the same
progressions. At least I do when I'm
like trying to write melodies and stuff
like that. And it would be so nice if I
can get to this seventh chord and blah
blah blah.
>> That's true.
>> Um,
>> if we just knew more in that way, I
think it would just broaden our, you
know,
>> especially with the Broadway stuff we're
writing, we're a little bit like, okay,
let's do a crash course in music theory
to be able to get where we need to get.
H
>> how do you guys listen to music
differently from an average person?
Listening, collecting, sampling.
>> I don't listen to a ton of music.
>> Really?
>> Yeah, I mostly listen to podcasts. Um
>> how I write. There we go. We can add it
to your podcast.
>> That's right. Yeah. Yeah. Um I guess the
music that I do listen to is like old.
It's like I listen to like a lot of like
barberhop quartet stuff like 1950s stuff
like Mellow Men like uh a lot of
Broadway stuff.
>> Um
>> if I send him a song I think he'll like
then he'll listen to that.
>> Yeah. Then I'll listen to that. Um I I
don't have a good answer for you of why
I don't really like listen to a lot of
music, but you listen to like
everything.
>> Tons. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I I'll go so
deep into Spotify of like the radio of
this of this of this and then I'll get
into like songs that have like no
streams and I just I like looking for a
great song, you know. Um and a lot of it
can blend together, but then when I find
that I'm going to go into I'm going to
listen to it a little scientifically.
First, I'll listen to it and just see if
I like it and then I'll kind of get that
feeling a little bit of
>> I think I'm missing that first step that
you're talking about where you're like
I'm just consuming like I feel like I
only can listen almost like I just know
too much about the production. I can
only listen for like cool snare they
used here as opposed to let me let this
thing wash all over me. Uh-huh.
>> It's just I find it so exciting that I
know there's going to be like I know
there's going to be one in the next
hundred that I listen to that's going to
be like, "Oh my god, a new song." And
there's nothing better than finding a
new song that you're obsessed with.
Where has this been my whole life that
that feeling? Um, so I'll let it wash
over me. I'll probably overlist to it
and I'll hate it in the after the 150th
listen, but I'll also be listening
pretty like scientifically in the back
of my mind. I just am obsessed with
knowing why I love it and uh listening
to a hook that I wish I had written. It
makes me so annoyed and excited.
>> So you follow the radio
>> of I'm talking about on Spotify.
>> Yeah. Like this artist's or this I think
you can do radio of songs. So we could
hear a song and like another radio.
>> Keep going and keep going and eventually
it really you will find artists that are
unknown. Well, it's crazy cuz I remember
when I got to college, there was a dorm
room of 10 of us and the entire status
game was who could find the coolest
music.
>> So, we were on different music blogs,
this song is sick, you know, whatever
else
>> and we would just hang out on Fridays
and Saturdays and Will and Vince in the
back, they just always had the best
music. So,
>> they, you know, if you had Ox Control,
like you were the coolest guy in the in
the group. And
now it doesn't feel at all like
there's any sort of social capital to be
gained in the same way from just finding
new music because it's all just sort of
on
>> on Spotify.
>> Yeah.
>> I mean, a lot of the songs I find are
pretty unknown and it makes me excited,
I guess, to send it to people.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Like I think that there's nothing
better than a good wreck. Like when you
recommend a movie to someone that they
like, it's like, "Oh god, it feels so
good. I did it.
>> You know that song Sign of the Times by
Harry Styles? I
>> when I heard that song for the first
time, it was like I was being born
again. I mean, just
it's the side of the types. It was so
grand. It was so
>> It was unlike anything else. It I
listened to it like a hundred times. The
the gift and the curse that I have is I
don't have the musical knowledge to get
caught on the snares and stuff. Like
sometimes I watch Rick Bat videos and he
did one about uh smells like teen spirit
of like and how that's how that's all
done. I'm like whoa.
>> Does that ruin the song for you a little
or enhance it?
>> Well, it makes me appreciate it more but
the problem is then that's the only
thing I know. So then that's the only
thing that I can kind of hear. And I
will say with writing, it's sometimes
harder for me to get lost in words
because just like you guys with sound,
I'm like that with paragraph transition,
sentence structure, word choice, all
that sort of stuff. It's
>> I can't turn off X-ray vision in my
reading,
>> but I don't have it when I listen to
music.
>> Yeah.
>> I don't know enough.
>> I I hear a lot of comedians talk about
jokes like that. Oh, I see what you did
there. You did a turn and that was a
classic missed whatever.
>> That's especially bad, I think, in
comedy. That's like where it goes to
dive, right? What is the dissecting the
frog? It's you learn how it works, but
you kill it in the process. Comedy%.
>> Yeah, I could see how that would ruin
joke. Especially jokes. Like, come on.
Let that thing just wash over you and
either laugh or don't laugh. Well, it's
sort of the the hard part of getting
good at something is you you lose your
childlike approach to it.
>> Totally.
>> Yeah. I think I've developed the ability
to go back and forth, honestly. I have
no idea. Just like it's I've almost
trained myself to I really think I can
listen from that stranger's point of
view. For some reason, I've developed
that ability and then I could listen
from Jack's point of view. And it it has
come from just watching and really
asking friends of their type of their
taste in music and having them recommend
songs to me and okay, I know what you
like. You must like this weird offbeat
kind of thing.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I think that's just one of my few
skills that I that I can contribute.
>> Such an interesting line that you walk
between this is the most extreme. I'm
the artist, I'll tell you what's good.
And it seems like you like this. It
seems like like the overeager. You have
to just constantly be going back and
forth in any kind of art and walking the
line. It has to be somewhere in the
middle of the two because if you were
just making music based on like seems
like people like this like we'd be a
pretty boring artist.
>> Totally.
>> But you need some of that. You You're
right. You need a little bit of that. a
little bit of that because there are a
lot of artists we see where like they're
like I make the art for myself
and like that can be dangerous because
don't you want your art to be seen by
other people and to connect with people?
That's too far in that extreme. Just
constantly riding that line.
Mhm.
Well, that's also in your guys
partnership is you're saying that you
come up with
the early words
and kind of create it and then you get
the feedback. The very fact that you
have each other means that you don't
need to play both sides all the time.
>> That's a really good point. Yeah.
>> Yeah. It's just I'm never thinking about
like I'm thinking like when I made world
smiles violent or whatever some of the
more like uncool kind of stuff like I'm
just thinking about how I feel in that
moment and that's the subconscious
creates the conscious edits like you
have to just be thinking about yourself
and then the next step is let me craft
this into something that's digestible
enough that people won't just turn it
off and be like this was a narcissistic
exercise. M
>> have you guys pulled from hip-hop in
terms of inspiration?
>> Yeah, 100%.
>> Definitely production.
>> Yes, for sure.
>> Beats-wise, but also like uh
honesty-wise, like um I I like our first
album that he talked about was like very
much us trying to figure out who we
were. We have a song, it's called Living
Room, the album. We have a song on
Living Room that's like so clearly an
Imagine Dragons copy. And this one is so
clearly a Beach Boys copy, like I was
saying.
And then I I think I was listening to
Mackmore at the time because it was
around that time and he just had all
these great stories on his first album
about uh this uh the shoe culture and
how someone was murdered for their Nikes
and like I remember being really jealous
of rappers that like wow you get to like
tell these stories that are so personal.
I'm yearning to be that personal, but we
I have to wrap it up in a verse, chorus,
verse, chorus, bridge, chorus, 3 minute
30 second catchy pop song.
>> Mhm. And then we wrote a song called
3:30.
>> And we wrote Yeah. Literally, we wrote a
song about that.
>> Yeah. About rappers have it easy because
they can kind of say whatever they want
>> in whatever phrasing they want and we
have to kind of keep it this way. And
>> and the fir along with 3:30, the first
moment of me
>> of us trying to like bridge that was a
song called Netflix Trip that's about
the office. is about the the TV show
which is another example of like a laugh
then cry and that felt like probably the
first moment where we were like okay I
can't it's not our life to talk about
someone being murdered for their Nikes.
I can't talk a lot about about the stuff
that most rappers talk about but here's
how I can get personal in something
that's truthful to me. How much a TV
show shaped the way I crossed my legs or
the way I hugged my mom at this age. Uh,
here's my way of getting as personal as
hip-hop can get.
>> Mhm. Who are the craziest, most faraway
artists that you guys pull from for
inspiration?
>> Um,
>> obviously you talk about the Beach Boys
and Imagine Dragons and there's things
you're pulling right in. Who is just
>> 7 million miles away?
>> Uh, there's a guy named Dan Reer that
we're really big fans of. He might be my
favorite artist. uh that is like a old
he's probably like in his 70s or
something. He like builds his own
guitars and he uh
>> he writes a lot of like the kind of
stuff that I'm talking about. Like he
would write a song from a dog's
perspective.
>> Um
>> but then there's also like the mellow
men too which is like barberhop quartet
which on our album Neothe
like fell in love with.
>> That's that like Peter Pan kind of 1950s
like Disney choir thing that we love.
How about musical theater? Do you guys
go to a lot of shows, Broadway shows?
>> Constantly.
>> Yeah. Constantly.
>> Yeah. Um, we grew up going and then
Yeah. I I think that there's like a a
feeling uh like in layiz uh where I
don't know if how much how well you know
Broadway, but like
uh in the show Lay Miz right before
intermission, they're all like about to
go off to war and they're going one day
more and it's like it ends and then the
audience like stands up and can't wait
to see the second half. That's like to
me that's pure emotion uncloaked by is
this cool that we're going we're off to
war like are we dressed cool like all of
that is diluting the pure emotion of
Fran it's about the revolutionary uh war
in France like France is coming together
to overthrow the upper class and like
they're all singing about it. Um to me
that kind of pure unadulterated emotion
is what I want to feel in our music.
Broadway really is just the place where
you have the most permission to be
expressive kind of with your body.
>> Yeah.
>> And with body and voice. And whenever I
go to a show, I'm just like,
>> "Wow." It's so grand. And it's
>> it's
>> And you don't get judged.
>> You don't get judged.
>> Yeah.
>> It's it's the new church. Like honestly,
like we grew up Jewish. Like we're not
necessarily like super religious. I've
been to church a few times. Like the
first time, this is just my experience.
The first time you're like looking
around at people that are like this and
you're you're like you roll your eyes a
little bit at it like cuz I don't know
cuz it's a new weird thing and then you
go a few more times and you're like,
"Oh, I'm the villain in this story."
Like like they're just being fully
themselves. Like who am I to like
look down on them? Um and and it turned
into like the most magical experience
ever. Like uh being in any sort of like
that is what religion is. It's like
we're all one big organism here and
there's no nothing like disconnecting
all of us. We're all just going to be
ourselves. That's how Broadway makes me
feel. And that's I think what we're
trying to do with the music.
>> Yeah. The other thing with Broadway,
I've been to a lot of shows this year
and what's cool about Broadway is it's
close enough to your guys work that you
can definitely pull from it, but it's
far away enough that other artists
probably probably aren't pulling from
it. And you know, if I was making a live
show, I'd be like, "Okay, I went and I
saw Hamilton. Hamilton had the rotating
stage. Maybe we do that. We have a
rotating stage for next live show. Okay,
I just went to Mulan Rouge and they have
the the actors and actresses on the
stage before the show begins. They're
just sort of walking around. Every time
I go to a live show, it's just dark.
Like, what do we how do we pull into
that? And now you just start going to
shows and every time I go to a Broadway
show, I always find one or two things
that I'm like, I'm going to add this to
my mental bank.
>> It's a lot of
>> things to do.
>> Totally. That literally happened. Uh
David Burn had a Broadway show a few
years ago like American Utopia where
there was like a curtain that came down
and a light down here and it shined like
a big shadow of him up there and he's
playing and I saw it with my girlfriend
at the time and I was like how cool
would it be if we all like believe that
this is his shadow if his shadow just
started doing different [__] than he was
doing started duetting her
>> and I just felt that as a consumer in
that moment. Then we literally just took
that and put it into uh Oh, maybe Mentor
last year.
>> I laugh because Maddian, who's one of my
favorite artists, he did a live show
called Good Faith Live and there's this
part inside the show where so he's
dressed as this black silhouette and the
lights behind him are really bright, so
you don't get a lot of depth and
dimensionality. And then what happens is
there's this white background and all of
a sudden you get like six to eight
Maddians. And I'm with my friend. I'm
like, where did they all
tricked? He's like, you guys really
totally tricked
>> and we're look at each other. Probably
last 10 to 12 seconds. And then all of a
sudden, they all disappear. And he's
standing right there in the middle. And
we just looked at each other being like,
whoa.
>> You know, we had just totally kind of
been burned or roasted by the artist and
I was like, yes,
>> that we love magic. Are you into just
magic in general? I hate magic.
>> I hate magic. It bothers me so much to
no end.
>> What's bothering you?
>> I just feel like I'm being tricked. I
can't figure it out. It's one of those
things where I think some people enjoy
that sensation. The fact that I can't
figure out infuriates.
>> That's why we know so many people like
that. I just cannot stand. Get it away
from me. Yeah.
>> I don't even want to do the exercise of
thinking how you could get that done.
And for us, it's like
>> if we could live in a world where that
guy could be nine people at once and
then this like what else is possible? I
don't know. It feels like that's we're
kids again.
>> Yes. Yes.
>> Yeah.
That's like, oh, okay, we don't
understand all of reality like and
that's fun. And and I think we like the
feeling of you trust us on stage because
we do a lot of magic and a lot of like
oh you thought we were going here. We
like we've established a trust
um and we've established that a
connection but like we're always one
step ahead of you. Um and I think
people I think nowadays especially with
the phones is I know
what my vacation is going to be before I
even go. Right? that I've booked out
everything and I've seen all the
pictures and I know what I'm in for. And
it's a really fun feeling to go to a
place and just not know what you're in
for. And a song ends and then suddenly
Jack's skydiving here or like in Magic
he takes out cards and then he puts that
away and then all of a sudden a an
elephant is here. Like to just be a kid
again consuming the world for the first
time and not knowing what you're in for.
Uh it's just so fun.
>> Yeah. Especially, yeah, we for our last
tour for maybe man, uh, uh, there there
was a whole narrative and sort of at the
end there's this big reveal of like a
50-foot version of Jack that we had this
like whole animatronic built and um, and
it was really tied into an emotional
story just about like sort of being the
biggest version of yourself and stuff
that our dad used to say to us. And um,
that was one where we kept really close
to the best. We're like, we tease a lot
on social media. Let's just have you be
there in the moment when that big it was
like looking over the audience when that
big thing
gets revealed. Let's have everybody just
be on the same page of bewilderment here
and start to think back. Oh, that's why
they were putting Easter eggs in the
show throughout to lead up to this
thing. Let's make everybody in the
audience little kids again in that
moment.
>> Yeah. How do you guys think about themes
on your album? Have you heard of the
album The Great American Bar Scene by
Zack Bryan?
>> No.
>> Okay. So, Zach is big country artist now
and
it's the album starts with a really
beautiful poem. I quite like it. I've
listened to the poem many times and he
talks about it and then the final word,
final line in the poem is the great
American bar scene. And it's cool
because the album starts and he sort of
creates the world of the great American
bar scene and then he sort of repeats
the line of the great American bar
scene. I've been grappling with was he
too explicit about the theme of the
album or do I really enjoy that it feels
cohesive or something? But is that
cohesiveness forced?
>> Right? Like is he trying too much? I I I
think that uh it's different per album
sometime. I mean actually I don't know.
I think we find it along the way. Like I
think with maybe man, we found it along
the way. We started writing a bunch of
songs that were like
what's the word? Like not aim a aimless
is the wrong word, but
>> all pointed in different directions.
>> Different directions. We didn't know
what it was. And then I think we wrote
this one song called Maybe Man or we
named it Maybe Man, the titular track.
Um and uh I think right away we realized
this is what the album is about. It was
about not knowing who we are as people.
we're this kind of person with our
friends and we're this kind of person
with our girlfriend and this and at the
end of the day who is the real me and I
think we were like okay this is the song
we're most resonating with right now
this should be the arc of the album and
then
not to go too dark and we won't but uh
throughout that process our dad got sick
and ended up passing away like while we
were making that album by the time we
wrote the last song for the album which
is 2085 that's a song about what we're
going to be like in 2085 when we're old
than like what will have been important
at the end of our life. And then there's
like a wrap-up to that first song of
like, oh, these are the things that are
important in life. And we only could
have learned that by watching, you know,
like everybody that came to my dad's
bedside like nobody said he was a great
architect. Everybody was like, he was
the nicest guy ever. He had this little
conversation with me. he like it really
is about these like small little moments
that you have with people and and and
sort of friendship and family. It's like
all this obvious stuff that now seems
obvious wasn't obvious to us when we
started the album. I feel like we like
literally learned that lesson along the
way. So, I think that that's that's part
of it. Be open to like changing the
course of like a lot of times when
people write movies by the end of the
movie they're like I didn't even realize
the movie was about this thing.
>> Yeah.
and be open to that because that will
give you the best movie.
>> That was so fun. It was so good to meet
you guys.
>> It was so good to meet you guys.
Amazing. Yeah, that was so fun.
>> We covered everything.
>> Yeah, covered a lot. It's just great to
hear how you guys think about things and
the freedom that you guys have, the joy
that you guys bring to the craft, the
goofiness. I really admire it. I hope we
can hang out in New York.
>> Let's do I'm sure we'll see each other
out the neighborhood. That was an
amazing interview. Yeah. Yeah. Thanks so
much. Thank you, man.